Guide to the Sierra Leone Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sierra Leone collection
1822-2009
MS 1541
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.31
(7 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence and printed material relating to the history of Sierra Leone and current political, economic, and social conditions. Also included are photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence and printed material relating to the history of Sierra Leone and current political, economic, and social conditions. Also included are photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Antislavery movements -- Great Britain; Slave trade -- Africa; Sierra Leone -- Economic conditions; Sierra Leone -- History -- To 1896; Sierra Leone -- Politics and government; Sierra Leone -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Sierra Leone
- Inventory, 1852-1993
  - Agreement between [Nathaniel Isaacs] and unidentified person(s) acquiring the right to cut timber, 1852 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1925, 1958-1959, [1984?], 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Albert Margai of Africa": biographical booklet, [1964-1967] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsletters, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Periodicals, popular, 1981, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Sierra Leone Democratic Party: bulletins, printed materials, 1984-[1985?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stevens, Siaka: presidential address, 1985 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspapers, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Periodicals, independent, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Momoh, Joseph Saidu: presidential address, 1990 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Paramount Chiefs of Sierra Leone: Photographic portraits by Vera Viditz-Ward": exhibition brochure, 1990 November 21-1991 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Leone Woman Magazine, first edition, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Nylander, Lyton: White paper on his report into the financial activities of the government, 1993 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Strasser, Valentine E. M.: Address on the occasion of the first anniversary of the April 29 revolution, 1993 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Davies, Beccles: White paper on his report into the assets of key officials of the state, 1993 August (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs: collection of seventy, partially identified, [1911?] (Box 1, Folder 16 - 17)
  - Photographs: mounted with descriptions, 1912-1914 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of native art, by Ben Oelmann, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Additional Material, 1822-1996; Accession 1995-M-199
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Includes accessions 1996-M-007, 1996-M-062, 1997-M-002, 1997-M-097, 1997-M-103, 1997-M-136, 1997-M-173, 1998-M-032, 1998-M-066, 1999-M-019, and 2000-M-035.
  - General information, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From the Committee on the Total Abolition of Slave Trade, 1822 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government papers
    - Address and statement by His Excellency Captain Valentine E. M. Strasser, 1993 April 29, November 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - At the court at Balmoral, 1877 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - At the court at Buckingham Palace, 1909 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - At the court at Carlton House, 1826 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - At the court at Windsor, 1824 October 19-1891 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Presidential addresses, 1988 June 3, 1990 June 8, 1996 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Report on Cooperation in Sierra Leone, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - White Paper on the Report of Justice Beccles Davies Commission of Inquiry, vols. 1, 2 [2 copies], and 3, 1993 Aug, Oct, 1994 February (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - White Paper on the Report of the Justice Lynton Nylander Commission of Inquiry, vols. 1 and 2, 1993 Apr, June (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - White Paper on the Report of the Mrs. Justice Laura Marcus-Jones Commission of Inquiry, 1993 January (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interim National Electoral Commission, Instructional Manual for Political Parties and Their Polling and Counting Agents, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interim National Electoral Commission, Sierra Leone General Elections, 1996 Voter's Guide (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Massaquoi, Siaka
    - SLPP: Triumphs and Trials, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      General
      SLPP stands for Sierra Leone Peoples Party.
    - The Historic Transition, March 1996: Welcome Tejan Kabbah and the SLPP, Farewell Brig. Gen. Bio and the NPRC (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Action Party, manifesto, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The National Unity Party, manifesto, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newspapers
    - The Champion, 1996 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The New Citizen, 1996 April 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Concord Times, 1996 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Expo Times, 1996 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Standard Times
      - Vol. 1, no. 31, 1996 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Vol. 2, no. 41, 1996 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Tell News, vol. 1, no. 3, 1996 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Weekly Echo, 1996 April 16-20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - We Yone, 1996 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Vision, 1996 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sesay, Habib M.
    - Economics Crisis and Its Impact on the Sierra Leone Society: General Overview and a Historical Analysis of the Recent Sierra Leone Economic Experience, 1990 April (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Perspectives of Political Developments in Sub-Saharan Africa: A Case Study of Sierra Leone, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sierra Leone Organization of National Archives [pamphlet], 1966 January (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Somaliland Protectorate
    - Financial statement of proposed development, 1955-1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Agreement with the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company, Limited and the Anglo-Egyptian Oilfields, Limited for the grant of an oil prospecting license and mining lease to the Somaliland Petroleum Company, Limited, 1928 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs
    - Freetown [negatives], 1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Photograph album compiled by Simmonds, Royal Air Force (RAF) member, made while in West Africa, 1942 June 3-1943 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Additional Material, 1926-1928; Accession 2004-M-037
  - Photograph album [approximately forty photographs with ink captions, possibly compiled by British expatriate, Howard Ross], 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1980-1993; Accession 2006-M-088
  - Links: Putting the Community in Touch, issue 10, 1993 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Paramount Chiefs of Sierra Leone", exhibit catalog of photographic portraits by Vera Viditz-Ward for National Museum of African Art, Smithsonian Institution, 1990 November 21-1991 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Poets of Sierra Leone, by Bowden Quinn for Institute of Current World Affairs, 1980 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Pujemun District Relief and Rehabilitation Agency (PUDRRA)", project proposal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sierra Leone Newsletter, Vol. 6, 1991 Winter/Spring (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journal of the English Department, Fourah Bay College, University of Sierra Leone, vol. 3, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of native population, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, 1963-2004; Accession 2011-M-051
  Arrangement
  Material arranged as received.
  - Newspapers
    - Concord Times, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Standard Times, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Exclusive, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Independent Observer, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Peep!, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - For di People, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Democrat, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Other publications
    - Ministry of Defense Quarterly News Bulletin, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - CRIVMON: Child Rights Violations Monitoring Network, 2002 Oct, 2003 Jun, November (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Background Information: Sierra Leone, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Royal Commonwealth Society, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Directory of the Social Sciences, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      People who have done work or had other research experience in Sierra Leone.
    - Local Government Elections 2004 Observer Kit, National Electoral Commission (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1971-2009; Accession 2015-M-001; 2.02
  - Printed material, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Posters, Circa 2000-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)